<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 8. Numb. 10. The continuation of our forraine intelligence, since the 3. of the last to this present Conteining many remarkable passages, amongst the rest these following. A more exact relation of the fearfull burning of the hill Soma nere Naples then the former, with the effects it hath wrought in that citie vpon the publicke harlots as well as other people. The adventure of the Imperiall Generall Pappenheim to relieue (or rather to ruine) the citie Magdenburg, with the successe thereof, as much as we haue yet received of credit. The late proceeding of the King of Sweden forces in Wittenburg, &amp; what townes he hath taken; his preparation and mooving, to meet with, and to prevent the designes of the imperialists nere Erford, and elsewhere. The state of the French K. in Lorraine, &amp; how he mooues. The late arrivall and royall entertainment of Monsieur the Kings brother at Bruxsell.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118676</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853883</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>February 8. Numb. 10. The continuation of our forraine intelligence, since the 3. of the last to this present Conteining many remarkable passages, amongst the rest these following. A more exact relation of the fearfull burning of the hill Soma nere Naples then the former, with the effects it hath wrought in that citie vpon the publicke harlots as well as other people. The adventure of the Imperiall Generall Pappenheim to relieue (or rather to ruine) the citie Magdenburg, with the successe thereof, as much as we haue yet received of credit. The late proceeding of the King of Sweden forces in Wittenburg, &amp; what townes he hath taken; his preparation and mooving, to meet with, and to prevent the designes of the imperialists nere Erford, and elsewhere. The state of the French K. in Lorraine, &amp; how he mooues. The late arrivall and royall entertainment of Monsieur the Kings brother at Bruxsell.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson?] for Nath: Butter and Nicolas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggested printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 11179.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11179 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustav, --  II, Adolf, --  King of Sweden --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19282:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19282:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>February</hi> 8. <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>THE CONTINVATION OF OVR FORRAINE <hi>INTELLIGENCE,</hi> ſince the 3. of the laſt to this preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conteining many remarkable paſſages, amongst the reſt theſe following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A more exact Relation of the fearfull burning of the hill <hi>Soma</hi> nere <hi>Naples</hi> then the former, with the effects it hath wrought in that Citie vpon the publicke Harlots as well as other people.</p>
            <p>The adventure of the Imperiall Generall <hi>Pappenheim</hi> to relieue (or rather to ruine) the Citie <hi>Magdenburg,</hi> with the ſucceſſe thereof, as much as we haue yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of Credit.</p>
            <p>The late proceeding of the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> forces in <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenburg,</hi> &amp; what Townes he hath taken; his preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and mooving, to meet with, and to prevent the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> nere <hi>Erford,</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
            <p>The ſtate of the <hi>French</hi> K. in <hi>Lorraine,</hi> &amp; how he moues.</p>
            <p>The late arrivall and royall entertainment of Monſieur the Kings brother at <hi>Bruxſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath: Butter</hi> and <hi>Nicolas Bourne.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reports">
            <pb facs="tcp:19282:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19282:2"/>
            <head>The Continuation of our Weekely NEWES.</head>
            <div type="report">
               <head>
                  <hi>From</hi> Lyons <hi>the</hi> 3. <hi>of</hi> Ianuary, 1631.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR King hath ſent to <hi>Paris</hi> for his royall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, either to hold his <hi>Entre</hi> at <hi>Nancy,</hi> or to viſit his Majeſtie of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Some thinke it is for an Election of a <hi>Roman King.</hi> We thinke therefore his Majeſtie will not come to <hi>Paris</hi> againe, before he hath quite ſubdued the Dukedome of <hi>Lorraine.</hi> And it is certaine, that the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique States, make earneſt ſuite for aſſiſtance from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie. And we thinke they will ſurely obtaine ſo much of him, that he will intercede with the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> to vſe no hoſtilitie againſt the Catholiques, and if he will be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereunto, we ſhall in time heare.</p>
               <p>They be very buſie in <hi>France</hi> in levying of Souldiers, and there be more commanded into <hi>Provence</hi> and <hi>Marſelles,</hi> whence it appeareth, that the next Summer there will be ſome warre in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Regensburg</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> Ditto.</head>
               <p>Many people retire themſelues from the vpper <hi>Palatinate</hi> hither; for that the Elector of <hi>Saxon</hi> is aboue eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtrong about <hi>Eger:</hi> And certaine Commiſſioners are ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived here, who place divers Souldiers along the river of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuby,</hi> and make their Quarters as farre as <hi>Paſſau,</hi> which the <hi>Bavarian</hi>-Countrymen much diſlike. And many vnmarried men are preſſed to the warres.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19282:3"/>
               <p>In the Land beyond the river of <hi>Ens,</hi> divers Imperiall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of foote and horſe are alreadie inquartered, and more expected. Wherefore the Boores there are very vnruly, and it is to be feared a Rebellion will ariſe among them.</p>
               <p>Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> is returned from <hi>Amberg</hi> to <hi>Nordlingen,</hi> to gather his Souldiers, to what intent time will declare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Leipſich</hi> the <hi>5.</hi> Ditto.</head>
               <p>Coronell <hi>Bannier</hi> vſed great force before <hi>Magdenburg,</hi> but the beſieged defend themſelues valiantly, in hope that <hi>Pappenheim</hi> (who already is arrived at <hi>Wolfenbutle</hi> with fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene hundred men, and hath taken out of the Garriſons here and there about eight thouſand men) would without fayle relieue them. Hee is marched already with divers Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments towards <hi>Halberſtadt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore the Duke of <hi>Weymar</hi> his Souldiers about <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> doe riſe to joyne themſelues with Colonell <hi>Bannier.</hi> Alſo the Duke of <hi>Lunenberg</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Bremen,</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Souldiers together, to ioyne with the ſayd <hi>Bannier</hi> to prevent <hi>Pappenheim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>Hamburg</hi> we vnderſtand, that thereabout are arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved divers thouſands of <hi>Swedes,</hi> who take their quarters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the river <hi>Elbe,</hi> and dayly expect more, and then will paſſe ouer the <hi>Elbe</hi> to beſiege <hi>Staaden,</hi> and <hi>Boxtehut;</hi> To which purpoſe the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> hath gathered a great number of men, and the ſayd Citties haue beene already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſurrender themſelues. And ſo they intend to ridd the Biſhoprick of <hi>Bremen,</hi> and land about the <hi>Weſer,</hi> of the <hi>Imperialiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> are not yet gone out of <hi>Wiſmar</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitz,</hi> the cauſe whereof is thought to be, that the Comiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they ſent vnto Collonell <hi>Tieffenbach</hi> concerning their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture is not yet returned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>
                  <hi>From</hi> Franckford <hi>the</hi> 6. <hi>of</hi> Ianuary.</head>
               <p>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> is yet (as we vnderſtand) at <hi>Mentz</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19282:3"/> giveth daily audience vnto thoſe Princes, Earles, and Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors that be there with him.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of <hi>Franckford</hi> haue obtained of the King not onely that they may retaine their old Imperiall priviledges and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. But alſo Proclamations haue beene publiſhed by the King, to let all men know, that all and every Merchant of what Religion or Nation ſoever they be, which deſire to traffique thither, may with their Merchandize at the time when the Mart is kept, or whenſoever they ſhall trade thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, paſſe and repaſſe without any moleſtation. And his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie hath thereupon given eſpeciall charge to the Officers and Souldiers not to hinder the ſame.</p>
               <p>The ſpirituall Electors are yet levying Souldiers, and thruſt themſelues into the King of <hi>France</hi> his protection, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince there is a <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour with the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> who requeſted that his Majeſtie would reſtore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpirituall Electors and Princes their Lands againe, and much inſiſted vpon the alliance betweene his King and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> But it ſeemes the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> doth not much regard it, and will nevertheleſſe not too ſoone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thoſe Countryes againe: And it may happen, that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> in recompence of his expences will detaine them and others the longer, for the better ſecuritie of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Vienna</hi> the <hi>7.</hi> Ditto.</head>
               <p>The Imperiall Army is now diſtributed into the hereditary poſſeſſions, although many complaints there haue bin made, yet all is referred vnto the Duke of <hi>Friedland;</hi> and moſt of the new levied Souldiers runne away, eſpecially the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> of which 16. Companies ranne away together at once, and haue done great hurt with pillaging in <hi>Moravia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Leipſich</hi> the <hi>7.</hi> Ditto.</head>
               <p>It is here reported, as if Colonell <hi>Pappenheim</hi> (who is about eight thouſand ſtrong) ſhould haue brought into <hi>Magden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19282:4"/> an hundred men foote and horſe, and aboue three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Waggons with proviſion, but no man will giue credit vnto it, becauſe Colonell <hi>Bannier</hi> lay neere vnto it with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of his Regiments, and the <hi>Weymariſh</hi> Souldiers who being about 6000. lay about <hi>Erford,</hi> marched towards <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia,</hi> to joyne themſelues with him.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Landgraue of <hi>Heſſen</hi> is arrived with his Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Weſer</hi> to follow <hi>Pappenheim,</hi> and therefore it is thought, they will rather bring <hi>Pappenheim</hi> into the middle of them, then that hee ſhould haue ſuccoured <hi>Magden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Franckford</hi> the <hi>10</hi> Ditto.</head>
               <p>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> paſſed by this way yeſterday towards <hi>Hanau</hi> to receiue his Queene (as is ſaid) who is daily there expected, and hath not ſeene the King in 19. moneths.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Swedes</hi> haue taken <hi>Germerſheim, Cronweiſen, Speier,</hi> and divers places more, they ſpeake alſo of <hi>Heydelberg,</hi> but it is not beleeved. The Marſhall of the field <hi>Horne</hi> hath blockt vp <hi>Schorndorfe</hi> in the Dukedome of <hi>Wirtemberg:</hi> and the Boores there are in Armes about 8000. ſtrong, to hinder the threatned Invaſion of Colonell <hi>Altringer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Forces are ſaid to lie 7. miles from <hi>Straſburgh</hi> ſtill, and we heare nothing of their marching.</p>
               <p>The Governour of <hi>Zaberne</hi> hath fortified himſelfe ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hath taken the Imperiall Souldiers into pay, that ran out of the Biſhopricke of <hi>Mentz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Naples,</hi> the <hi>6.</hi> of Ianuary.</head>
               <p>Vpon Tueſday morning about one of the clocke, being the 16. of <hi>December,</hi> the Mountaine of <hi>Soma</hi> about 6. miles from <hi>Naples</hi> brake forth into a very ſtrange and marveilous burning, wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully aſtoniſhing the Inhabitants round about; and continued with great violence for the ſpace of two daies covering, or rather burning the neighboring Townes round about with aſhes therof: many both men women &amp; children burned, multitudes leaving their habitations, eſcaped onely with their liues, fleeing with their children to <hi>Naples</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19282:4"/> where indeed thoſe of this Citie haue not wonted to extend their Charitie towards the diſtreſſed in ſuch abundant meaſure. The horſes, oxen, ſheep, &amp; other annimals left behind them, were all deſtroyed by the fires extremitie; the which evaporated forth moſt hideous noyſe, much like Thunder, or the noyſe of great Ordnance, which we of <hi>Naples</hi> heard as eaſily as if we had beene cloſe by it. The force of this fire was ſuch, that it ſent forth pieces of the Mine weighing aboue an hundred weight two miles diſtant from the place. I ſpoke with them that out of curioſitie went within 3. miles of the Mount, but ſuch pieces fell neere vnto them, checking their hardineſſe, that feare cauſed their retyre with great aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But that which hath adminiſtred moſt terror, was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of Earthquakes ever ſince the Mount began to burne the moſt violent were the firſt two dayes, which happened once in a quarter of an houre, which ſo far affrighted the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apolitants,</hi> that they greatly feared the ſinking of the City, or the falling downe of their houſes vpon their heads. Many therefore fled out of the City into other remote places, the Viceroy purpoſing to doe the like was prevented, becauſe not thought fit of the Collaterall. Many through feare ſought out vacant places, where they might repoſe themſelues in their clothes in the night ſeaſon, others building ſheds of boards to ſhelter themſelues: for the ſpace of two houres the Levant windes, that is the Eaſt, blew the ſmoake towards the City, which much obſcured the ayre, and the ſtreets almoſt an inch thicke with aſhes which came from the Mount: and if the wind had continued, it would haue driven, or cauſed all the people to haue fled out of the City; but a Ponnent wind that is a Weſt hapned, thanked be God it hath not much annoyed the City, but hath burnt vp a great part of the Country. The aſhes I am credibly informed extending to <hi>Burletta,</hi> which is aboue 60. Engliſh miles from the place: ſince the firſt two dayes the Earthquakes are not ſo frequent, neither ſo violent, but do ſtill continue. Evident are the demonſtrations of their humiliation. It were incredible to relate the number of their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19282:5"/> proceſſions, for their great and numberleſſe tranſgreſſions; and that by the people of every condition, in divers manners. Some by the Viceroy and Nobilitie were performed in moſt ſolemne manner; ſo alſo by the Cardinall on his bare feete, with other of the Clergie: great quantity of men moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly whipping themſelues vp and downe in token of their humilitie. Many were the men alſo that in pennitentiall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits went bare footed in their proceſſions: ſo in like manner women with their haire hanging looſe about their eares; and of theſe the greateſt part were whores, which for number are more then a good many, being eſtimated to bee aboue 40. thouſand (ſome are of opinion many more) thirty thouſand are regiſtred, and pay the <hi>Gabella.</hi> Their proceſſions were day and night, grieveous and dolefull were their cryes in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. By the commaund of the Viceroy all ſhops were ſhut in for foure dayes, and every one to devote themſelues to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, praying, and pious actions: and that if any ſhould be found in the houſe of a whore, to forfeit 2000. Duckets, and the whore to be whipt about the City, &amp; baniſhed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Men not able to pay the penaltie, to be ſent to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; (as a thing moſt rare) the whores confeſſe themſelues in great abundance, ſome retire into Monaſteries, many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and great hope of reformation expected. In fine the hill is much conſumed, and continueth burning, the vent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much inlarged, and Earthquakes (God be thanked) ceaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Regooza</hi> the <hi>17.</hi> of December.</head>
               <p>The 17. of this preſent in the morning was found here in <hi>Regooza,</hi> and the Territories thereof, aſhes which covered all the ground over halfe an inch thicke, and had a burning-ſent, and that day continued darkiſh, with ſome ſmall raine, and about two of the clocke in the after-noone began to darken more and more, ſo that about halfe an houre after two it was as darke as midnight, which made all the people for feare flie into the Churches, where they remained till ſomewhat paſt three, for then it began to cleere, and ſuddenly appeared light againe. As yet we doe not heare whether it hath beene ſo in other parts hereabouts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19282:5"/>
               <head>Extract of a Letter written at <hi>Sultsbach</hi> the <hi>12.</hi> of <hi>Ianuary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> arrived yeſterday at <hi>Ambeg,</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied by about 50. horſes, hee came thither in his Coach from <hi>Newmarke.</hi> It is ſaid there are following after him 2000. horſe. With whom he intends to goe to <hi>Weyden.</hi> wherein there is already a great Garriſo n thence to view the conveniency for forming therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout of a Campe, and perhaps to viſite the <hi>Saxonian</hi> forces that lye enquartered about <hi>Eger;</hi> To which end this very night the horſe that lye hereabout have bin commanded to march towards <hi>Neuſtadt</hi> neare <hi>Weyden,</hi> to be muſtered.</p>
               <p>Generall <hi>Gallas,</hi> who doth now command ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall forces in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> lyeth at this time with his forces about <hi>Plau, Daus, Cladra, Darhaw</hi> and <hi>Heyd</hi> which is but one dayes journey from <hi>Weyden.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Saxonian</hi> forces have need to be watchfull and ready when theſe gueſts ſhall come to viſite them.</p>
               <p>Among <hi>Tillyes</hi> forces, that lye in their winter quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Countrey called <hi>Ries</hi> and about <hi>Donawert,</hi> the plague beginnes to be very fierce. But yet we heare they are not ſo much affrighted thereby as they are onely by the name of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> of whoſe comming they cannot abide to heare.</p>
               <p>The Maieſtrate of <hi>VVeyden</hi> having kept in their cuſtodie the keyes of their gates (although they have an Imperiall Garriſon with them) have beene forced to deliver the ſame up unto Collonell <hi>Linloch,</hi> who commands the ſaid garriſon; But becauſe it was feared the inhabitants will take it ill and perhaps undertake to beate the ſaid garriſon out, the keyes were reſtored backe againe to the Maieſtrate: But to aſſure the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full garriſon, the burgers and inhabitants are this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day to deliver up their armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Mentz the laſt of December.</head>
               <p>I forgot in my laſt to tell you, that there was found in the Caſtle of <hi>Konigſtein</hi> (which as I told you former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19282:6"/> was laſt weeke ſurrendred to Land-grave <hi>VVilliam</hi> of <hi>Heſſen</hi>) ſuch ſtore of all ſorts of Victualls, Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; faire braſſe pieces of Ordnance. That we cannot marvell enough that the garriſon that was in it did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the ſame, ſince they had all manner of proviſions of all neceſſaries both for mans ſuſtenance and recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſufficient ſtore for more then a whole yeare. On Chriſtmas evening there arrived heere to the King, <hi>Palatine Auguſtus</hi> and Duke <hi>Adolph Frederic</hi> of <hi>Mec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelburg.</hi> And there are many other young Princes here Who for the moſt part take commiſſions to leavie forces for his ſaid Maieſty. And verily the leavies doe very well goe on (as we underſtand from many brave and valorous Colonels) and there have alſo beene late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given ſpeciall Commiſſions unto ſome whom I may not as yet name here, to have generall Command over certaine forces this comming ſpring, at which time his Royall Maieſty hoping to bring into the field (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the army of the Elector of <hi>Saxen</hi> which is to conſiſt aboue thirty thouſand men) at the leaſt three hundred Cornets and five hundred Enſignes, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment wherof you may thinke will amount to an exceeding, yea infinite expenſe: Seeing the Army which his Maieſty doth at this time maintaine, doth coſt about 150. Millions of dollars a yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>
                  <hi>In</hi> Amſterdam 4. <hi>February,</hi> 1631.</head>
               <p>Letters from <hi>Cullen</hi> arriued this day, doe certifie us that <hi>Pappenheym</hi> the Emperors Generall had brought into <hi>Magdenburg</hi> 2. or 300. Wagons, and in marching out of the City againe, were encountred by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander <hi>Bannier,</hi> who hath rooted them and taken the ſayd Generall <hi>Papenheym</hi> Priſoner, upon which the Garriſon which was within <hi>Magdenburg</hi> fled. But the truth hereof we muſt expect with the next.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Hamborough</hi> here arrived paſſengers yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, who have not beene long from thence, which doe affirme, that before their departure from thence, they had certaine tydings, that the Garriſon which was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19282:6"/> within <hi>Magdenburg,</hi> were fled from thence, having left behind them but 4. pieces of Ordnance, that were ſerviceable, the reſt they have nayled, and caſt into the <hi>Elve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was in <hi>MentZ,</hi> having beene with his Queene at <hi>Hanaw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have tidings that the Biſhop of <hi>Trier</hi> is agreed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Antwerp.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> the French Kings brother arrived at <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſels</hi> on the 28. of Ianuary in the afternoone about 4. of the clocke, and was received with great magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, the Burgers went in their Armes about one league and a halfe to meete him.</p>
               <p>He made his entry on horſe-backe, being cloathed in gray, and a buffe-coller.</p>
               <p>The troopes to receive him were of 3. ſorts. The firſt were with Gentlemen with whom went the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of <hi>Monſieur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond conſiſted of the Marquis <hi>Mirabell,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yton.</hi> Marquis <hi>de Balanſon,</hi> Prince of <hi>Braban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Simey,</hi> and all the Nobility of the Court.</p>
               <p>In the third came <hi>Monſieur</hi> himſelfe, accompanied by the Marquis <hi>de la Cruce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Don Carlos Coloma,</hi> with ſome Nobility and her highneſſe guard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Leypſich</hi> the <hi>15.</hi> of Ianuary, <hi>1632.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Imperialiſts have quitted <hi>Magdenburg,</hi> but before their departure they did all the ſpoile they could, they pulled downe all the ſteeples, brake the windowes, and alſo the goodly Organs, and tooke away the pipes, ſet the roofe on fire but it would not burne. They alſo under-mined the bulworke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Deck,</hi> they brake with a petardo, the Ducer and <hi>Sudenberger</hi> gates. Divers peeces of Ordnance which they could not take along with them, they nayled up, and caſt ſome of them into the river <hi>Elbe.</hi> And now three Companies of Swediſh Souldiers are put into the remnant of the Cittie.</p>
               <p>And while <hi>Papenheym</hi> withdrew himſelfe to <hi>Wolfen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buttle</hi> the Swediſh Army followed him at the heeles.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19282:7"/> And it is reported they have had already an encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And <hi>VVolfenbuttle</hi> they ſay is blockt up.</p>
               <p>The Countrey people on both ſides are very much waſted, but ſeeing the paſſage of Lower <hi>Saxony</hi> unto the <hi>VVeſer</hi> is free againe, the pooore people recover a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Bohemia</hi> the Souldiers dye apace, but daily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes come hither againe.</p>
               <p>His highneſſe the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> with two Dukes of <hi>Saxon Altenburg</hi> are heere, with many Officers more. But they will depart hence within theſe two dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>
                  <hi>From</hi> Franckford 21. <hi>Dito.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>His Maieſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> with his Royall Conſort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned ſafe hither from <hi>Gelhenhauſen</hi> yeſterday in the evening, and were received with peeces of Ordnance; His Maieſty is daily waited on by divers Princes and Ambaſſadors from great Potentates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>Leypſich 18. <hi>Dito.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This day were ſent from hence tenne peeces of Ordnance to <hi>Torgaw,</hi> among which were foure halfe Canons, with tenne horſes to each peece, and foure to each of the other, and many Wagons with munition, which were taken from <hi>Tilly.</hi> And it is reported, that on Thurſday laſt the garriſon of <hi>VViſmar</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And that <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>penheim,</hi> Count <hi>VVolffe</hi> of <hi>Mansfelt</hi> are in <hi>VVolfenbutt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>
                  <hi>Laus Deo</hi> Franckford 25. <hi>January</hi> 1632.</head>
               <p>On Tweſday laſt at night the Queene of <hi>Sweede</hi> came unto <hi>Hannaw</hi> where the King of <hi>Sweed</hi> met her and ſtayed two nights and ſo both marched forward towards <hi>Erfort</hi> and ſome ſay towards <hi>Bamberg</hi> who did take out of every Regiment certaine forces, and ſome out of this Citty to the value of 600. Men ſo that his Army will be that marcheth with the King ſome 25000. what ſhould be the cauſe that hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched away from us, is as it is reported that <hi>Pappenheim</hi> is with 10000. men marched and hath releeved <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19282:7"/> and that the Marquis <hi>Hammilton</hi> with <hi>Banier,</hi> were compelled to leave the ſiege, &amp; to retire to ſome advantage and ſo <hi>Magdenburg</hi> was releeved, but ſome report ſince that the Marquis <hi>Hammilton</hi> with the Duke <hi>VVeymar</hi> and <hi>Banier</hi> hath beaten <hi>Papenheim</hi> but at large of this day the letters doth come; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Crabats had an Enterprize of <hi>Prague</hi> but the D. of <hi>Saxe</hi> his forces having notice of it met them at the <hi>VVelſſenberg</hi> and cut them off and tooke 4. Ancients and at <hi>Eger</hi> Coronell <hi>Merodes</hi> regiment did thinke to doe ſome enterprize but was beaten by the Duke of <hi>Saxe</hi> his forces before <hi>Eger,</hi> the forces of <hi>Tilly</hi> lye in the upper <hi>Palatinate</hi> ſometime in one place ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in another place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bobenhauſen</hi> is with all accord taken in by the Count of <hi>Jſenberg,</hi> many French Ambaſſadors hath beene with the King of Sweed but what was the matter I know not, but it is ſpoken that the King of Sweed is gone againſt <hi>Bamberg</hi> becauſe the Biſhop did not keepe his accord with the King of <hi>Sweed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Newes is yeſterday that <hi>Papenheim</hi> is beaten and hath loſt all his baggage and that the King of <hi>Sweed</hi> is returning backe towards <hi>Hannaw</hi> againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From <hi>Stetin</hi> the <hi>30.</hi> of December.</head>
               <p>Both <hi>Wiſmar</hi> and <hi>DamitZ</hi> (as you know townes of great conſequence in <hi>Meckelburg</hi>) are now delivered from the Imperialiſts, having beene delivered up this weeke. So that the forces that were imployed in the ſiege thereof may now be elſewhere imployed by the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>A letter written at <hi>Prague</hi> the <hi>25.</hi> of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſtil. vet.</head>
               <p>I would often haue written unto you, but that I know no letters could paſſe. Now underſtanding the poſts are againe eſtabliſhed, according to the former courſe, from hence to <hi>Dreſden,</hi> I will againe returne to my wonted courſe and write unto you every week. And to make a beginning, you may be pleaſed to know,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19282:8"/> That on the thirteenth of this preſent Moneth there arrived ſevearll troopes of <hi>Crabats</hi> here before the gate called the gate of <hi>Wiſſenberg</hi> (or white-hill) and intended to ſurpriſe or take the Towne by force, whereupon three pieces of Ordnance (which is the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or warning of the enemies approach) being ſhot off. The Colonell Commander of the Towne, a Baron of <hi>Hofkirk,</hi> ſent out ſome companies of horſe which ſell on the enemy, who quickly betooke himſelfe to flight, leaving many dead and ſome priſoners behind them. The next day (the 14.) the enemy arrived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in good earneſt, having placed behind the Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, about 1000. Muſquetiers, and about 1000. Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons to flanke them. There the enemy approaching neare the Towne, found preſently ready to receive him. The two Companies of horſe of <hi>Arnheyms</hi> his guard, and ſome other troopes, who had placed ſome Muſquetiers into ſome low ground. Now the ſaid two horſe Companies of <hi>Arnheym</hi> having met with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, turned quickly backe and fled, and the enemy purſuing them eagerly, paſſe neare the place, where the Muſquetiers lying hidden, ſaluted them ſo ſuddenly, that a great many tumbled downe from their horſes, and the reſt began to flye backe; Whereupon the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my with a reaſonable Army appeared on the high ground, and made ſhew as if he intended to take the Towne by force. Then our forces were brought back into the Towne, and all things prepared for defence. Every one taking his appointed places both in the new Sconces and in the fortifications, and the Governour of the little Towne, being a Count of <hi>Solms</hi> cauſed two field pieces to be placed upon a high houſe in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, whereby he did ſo trouble ſome troupes of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy that came neare; that ſeeing all was to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him, he made againe his retreat. Now when we ſaw that he was turning backe, our horſe being ready
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19282:8"/> to fall out upon the enemies Reere, then preſently the Ieſuites began to ring the bels of their Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the enemy had a mind to come againe on, but our Ordnance doing great harme amongſt him, he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quite away; And the Governours and Magiſtrates ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all poſſible and ſpeedy paines to know the reaſon of the Ieſuites ringing, they found out that the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites had had an intelligence and conſpiracy with the enemy. Whereupon their Colledge being viſited, there was found great proviſion of munition and of Armes, for many hundred men, which were ready to bee uſed both by the Ieſuites themſelves and others their friends, who endeavoured to make ſome troubles and would have made a great uprore, (had the enemy got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten one gate or any entry into <hi>Prague</hi>) to favour his deſigne, and to helpe to kill thoſe within the Towne. Thus God having delivered us, and diſcovered their treaſon, there was preſently on the very ſame day pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a prohibition that no Bell at all ſhould more bee rung in the three Townes of <hi>Prague,</hi> and that none ſhould be ſuffered to goe out or to come in, untill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order.</p>
               <p>On the 15. of this, there were put certaine compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſouldiers, as for Garriſon into the two Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Ieſuites in <hi>Prague,</hi> the one whereof is built in the old Towne, and the other in the little Towne.</p>
               <p>On the ſixeteenth the Magiſtrates viſited the ſayd Colledge, and found many warlike proviſions and Inſtruments. Whereupon it was conſulted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded they ſhould bee ſent out of the Towne yet that Evening: And indeed there were already divers Coaches and Waggons ready before their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for the tranſport of thoſe irreverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Traytors which I ſaw my ſelfe. —
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19282:9"/> But it was delayed untill the next morning. And ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>On the 17 very early executed, and all Ieſuites ſent away, ſo that now we are rid of that plague. Their Colledge of the little Town is now given unto and in the poſſeſſion of the Carmelites, who dwelled before in the Dutch Church, given to them ſoone after the battell of <hi>Prague,</hi> and the Ieſuites Colledge of old <hi>Prague</hi> ſell to the ſhare of the <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryers, who are very well content of it.</p>
               <p>Thurſday laſt the Lord of <hi>Hofkirch</hi> cauſed the firſt Sermon to be preached againe in the Dutch Church of the old Towne, and after Sermon his Lordſhip and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Noblemen, Officers and great multitude of people received the Communion.</p>
               <p>The foreſaid Count of <hi>Solms,</hi> being a very provident and wiſe man, cauſed the yce of the River of <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da</hi> to be broken up, that there is no paſſage neyther for root nor for horſe, he hath alſo cauſed ſome Ordnance to be placed upon the White Tower, which he hath cauſed to be mended, whereby we hope to withſtand the enemy, and keepe the Towne.</p>
               <p>The Boores are very reſolute in the Country, and they diſcover and ſearch out all ſuch as are affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the enemy, ſome they Dill, ſome they take Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and bring them to be examined. Yeſterday they brought a Priſoner who had tyed certaine Letters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his privy parts, which Letters I know not what they contained, but the carrier is to be hangd.</p>
               <p>Now we receive newes, that the Imperialiſts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to take <hi>Brande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> have beene well beaten for their labour by our Garriſon that lyes there, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting onely of three hundred Muſquetiers of the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Regiment.</p>
               <p>Thus much for this time, the next Weeke I hope I ſhall ſend you yet better newes, but I wiſh to know whether or no you receive my Letters</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19282:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19282:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
